Guide to the Frances Patai Audio Collection ALBA.AUDIO.131
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frances Patai Audio Collection
1985-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Patai, Frances
ALBA.AUDIO.131
0.5 Linear Feet (36 audiocassettes)
Frances Patai was an educator, writer, historian and feminist activist. Born in New York in 1930, she earned her bachelor's and master's degrees at the City College of New York in the 1950s and taught English and Communication courses throughout the City University of New York (CUNY) system. Patai was deeply concerned with human rights issues, in particular the rights and status of women, and in the last decade of her life she devoted her efforts to researching and writing a book on U.S. women medical personnel who volunteered during the Spanish Civil War. The oral histories that make up this collection are part of her extensive research material. The collection consists of interviews with volunteers from the Spanish Civil War, primarily the women who served as nurses.
Historical/Biographical Note
Frances Patai was born on New York City's Lower East Side in 1930. As a teenager, she performed in Jewish resorts in the Catskills as an actress and dancer. In her twenties she attended classes at the City College of New York, earning her bachelor's degree in 1955 and her MA in 1957. Beginning in the 1970s she served as an English and Communications instructor at various institutions in the City University of New York (CUNY) system, including long-term appointments at John Jay College and the Borough of Manhattan Community Colleges.
Throughout her career Patai was concerned with the rights and status of women, addressing in a series of essays and articles issues related to rape, pornography, and abuse. During the 1980s she worked with the feminist organization Woman against Pornography, serving as spokesperson and organizing their annual WAP Awards, an event that promoted the non-sexist representation of women in advertising. In later life Patai turned her attention to the anti-fascist movements of the 1930s, and began to investigate the history of American volunteers who joined the Republican forces to fight against Franco's army during the Spanish Civil War. Patai focused her attention on the participation of American women volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, devoting her efforts to researching and writing a book on the contributions of nurses. Through her friendship with Fredericka Martin -- a nurse with the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy who collected extensive biographical material on her former colleagues -- Patai gained access to unique primary materials, and to the surviving nurses themselves. She conducted these interviews over several years, as part of her research project.
Patai died in 1998 before she could bring her project to fruition. She was 67 years old.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fredericka Martin Papers (ALBA 001) Julia Newman: "Into the Fire" Research Files (ALBA 226) Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131) Frances Patai Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 131) Frances Patai File in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive (ALBA) Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 36 audiocassettes, which were separated from the Francis Patai Papers (ALBA 131). The interviews were conducted by Patai in the period 1985 to 1992, in the course of research for her book project on U.S. women medical personnel who vounteered during the Spanish Civil War. Most are with the women who volunteered as nurses, but also included are interviews with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans Moe Fishman and Steve Nelson, and with Marion Wachtel, widow of ALB volunteer Robert Merriman. Drafts of Patai's planned book, and her article "Heroines of the Good Fight: Testimonies of U.S. Volunteer Nurses in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939" (Nursing History Review, 3 (1995): 79-104), which utilizes the interviews in this collection, can be found in the Patai Papers (ALBA 131). Also included in the collection are tapes of a conference and a veterans' dinner, and a recording of Spanish Civil War songs.
Arrangement
Each recording has been assigned a unique item number (e.g., ALBA A 131-001), and the collection is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the interviewee. (Women's maiden names, or names used during service in Spain, are listed first -- followed by names used later in life.)
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The audiovisual materials in the collection were digitized by the Barbara Goldsmith Preservation and Conservation Department in 2019. Digital access copies are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Americans |z Spain |x History |y 20th century.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American |v Interviews.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Patai, Frances; Martin, Fredericka I.
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda, Jan 15, 1991; cuid14393; 316101 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-001, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda; Mildred Rackley (Simon), Jan 14, 1991; cuid14394; 316102 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-002, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Davidow, Ruth, Jan 20, 1992; cuid14395; 316103 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-003, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14395)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 94 minutes
- Fisher, Ruth and Harry, May 21, 1988; cuid14396; 316107 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-007, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14396)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 48 minutes
- Fishman, Moe (Moses), Nov 6, 1989; cuid14397; 316108 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-008, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14397)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 43 minutes
- Freeman (Feinberg), Helen, Apr 20, 1990; cuid14398; 316106 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-006, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14398)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 34 minutes
- Goldin (Spiegel), Irene; Esther Brown, Jan 22, 1991; cuid14399; 316131 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-034, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14399)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 59 minutes
- Gonzala, Garcia Delgado, Jul 15, 1988; cuid14400; 316109 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-009, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14400)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 46 minutes
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, Apr 23, 1990; cuid14401; 316112 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-013, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14401)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 62 minutes
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, Apr 23, 1990; cuid14402; 316113 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-014, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14402)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 12 minutes
- Klavantz, Rae, Jul 1991; cuid14403; 316114 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-015, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14403)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 57 minutes
- Leight, Clara, Dec 17, 1986; cuid14404; 316115 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-016, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14404)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 90 minutes
- Leight, Clara, Dec 17, 1986; cuid14405; 316116 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-017, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14405)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 64 minutes
- Levine (Hartzman), May, Jan 27, 1991; cuid14406; 316117 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-018, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14406)
  Scope and Contents
  On Side 2 of this tape, May Levine Hartzman and Sidney Kaufman are interviewed separately.
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 68 minutes
- Malbin, Virginia, 1985; cuid14407; 316118 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-019, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14407)
  Preservation Note: "From beginning to 00:1:30, tape rewinds and repeats part of the conversation."
- Malbin, Virginia, Jan 25, 1991; cuid14408; 316141 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-021, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14408)
- Malbin, Virginia; Esther Silverstein (Blanc), Jan 25, 1991; cuid14409; 316119 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-020, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14409)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 53 minutes
- Martin, Fredericka, undated; cuid14410; 316120 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-022, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Martin, Fredericka, Oct 8, 1989; cuid14411; 316121 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-023, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records 131ref22_024)
- Merriman (Wachtel), Marion, Feb 3, 1991; cuid14412; 316122 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-024, Box ALBA Shared Access Box 1)
- Nelson, Steve, Apr 19, 1991; cuid14413; 316123 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-025, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14413)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 95 minutes
- Nelson, Steve, Apr 19, 1991; cuid14414; 316142 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-026, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14414)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 6 minutes
- North (Green), Helen; Spanish Civil War Songs, May 8, 1987; cuid14415; 316110 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-010, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14415)
- Rackley (Simon), Mildred, Jan 14, 1991; cuid14416; 316129 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-032, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14416)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 47 minutes
- Rolfe, Mary, Jan 18, 1991; cuid14417; 316124 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-027, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14417)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 44 minutes
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, Feb 21, 1987; cuid14418; 316111 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-011, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14418)
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, May 15, 1992; cuid14419; 316140 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-012, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14419)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 52 minutes
- Sendor, Andrea (Sister Benedicta), May 15, 1990; cuid14420; 316125 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-028, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14420)
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca, Jan 26, 1991; cuid14421; 316104 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-004, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14421)
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca; Helen Freeman (Feinberg), Jan 27, 1991; cuid14422; 316105 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-005, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14422)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 70 minutes
- Shuldiner (Goldman), Anne, May 22, 1990; cuid14423; 316126 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-029, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14423)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 83 minutes
- Silverstien (Blanc), Esther; Sana Goldblatt, Jan 17, 1991; cuid14424; 316127 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-030, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14424)
- Silverstein (Blanc), Esther; Mary Rolfe, Jan 18, 1991; cuid14425; 316128 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-031, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14425)
- Temple, Lenora, Dec 13, 1986; cuid14426; 316132 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-035, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14426)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 92 minutes
- Spanish Civil War Conference, Mar 19, 1988; cuid14427; 316130 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-033, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14427)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 54 minutes
- VALB: 55th Anniversary Dinner, Apr 26, 1992; cuid14428; 316133 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-036, E-records tamwag_alba_audio131, E-records cuid14428)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 25 min.